Finding Aid for St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) Records, 1884-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1884-2006
St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Church formed in 1971 from the merger of two Detroit, Michigan, Episcopal parishes. Records include historical and informational files; vestry minutes and treasurer's records; records of church organizations; publications and church bulletins; subject files; scrapbooks; and photographs.
89513 Ba 2
14 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 7722 ) came to the library, September 1989. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open for research.
In 1971, two of Detroit's most historically significant and influential Episcopal churches merged to form St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church.
St. Matthew's, the older of the two congregations, claims the distinction of being the third oldest Black church in the state of Michigan. Established in 1846 by the Reverend William C. Monroe, William Lambert, and other former members of Second Baptist Church, St. Matthew's Mission (as it was then called) played an active role in the education and spiritual support of the Black community of Detroit. The church, along with Second Baptist, was prominent as one of the stations on the underground railroad that shepherded fleeing slaves northward, out of the South and, from Detroit, across the border into Canada.
During its first decade, the membership of St. Matthew's was small and subject to sudden fluctuation, particularly as its members felt threatened by provisions of the Fugitive Slave Law that could have returned them into bondage. Monroe, more than anyone else, maintained St. Matthew's as a viable church body, and when he resigned as vicar in 1859 to depart for Liberia as a missionary, St. Matthew's Mission experienced further decline. In 1864, the mission liquidated its assets. Some of the faithful continued to meet at Christ Church as the Sunday School of St. Matthew's, but in reality, from 1864 to 1880, the mission had ceased to exist.
In 1880, the mission was revived, formal ties being established with the Michigan Diocese of the Protestant Episcopal Church. Services were first held in a rented hall. Then in 1881 the mission was moved to the site it would occupy for the next ninety years at the corner of St. Antoine and Elizabeth. In 1882, J. Mott Williams became the first regular pastor of the reorganized congregation.
Throughout the nineteenth century, St. Matthew's, within the hierarchy of the Episcopal Church, was an organized mission. Then in 1907, following formal application and consideration by the Convention of the Diocese of Michigan, St. Matthew's obtained parish status, administratively responsible to the diocese and now governed by a vestry board chosen by its members.
Although beset by continual financial worries, St. Matthew's grew in membership and importance to the community. After World War II, however, the church began experiencing the effects of shifts in the city's population. In addition to the movement of some of its members from the city to the suburbs, urban renewal was a further source of community disruption. To survive, church leaders realized that they would have to revitalize their ministry, and perhaps most importantly, find new facilities. By the late 1960s, under the leadership of St. Matthew's rector, the Reverend Quintin E. Primo, Jr., negotiations were opened with St. Joseph's, another similarly struggling parish, to discuss the possibility of a merger.
The origins of St. Joseph's Episcopal Church can be traced to a commemorative chapel which Mrs. Lucetta Medbury gifted to the Episcopal Church in 1883. At first used only as a Sunday school, the members of St. Joseph's Memorial Chapel soon began considering whether to formalize its relationship to the Episcopal Church. Following consultations with the bishop, who gave them directives on the required number of members and the amount of pledge money needed, the members of St. Joseph's Memorial Chapel, on October 25, 1884, came together to form a new church to be called St. Joseph's Memorial Mission. The Reverend William J. Speiers was the Mission's first rector, followed by E. Breddon Hamilton and Louis Arthur.
In the 1890s, most of the members of St. Joseph's merged into St. Paul's which Bishop Charles Williams had designated as his cathedral. In 1906, some of the church's former members decided to re-establish St. Joseph's at a different location, in the rapidly-growing area along Woodward Avenue, north of Grand Boulevard. This parish grew, and in 1926, moved into its new facility on Woodward Avenue between Holbrook and King Streets.
The church in the coming decades acquired a reputation of being open to the needs of the people of the neighborhood. As the parish changed, the rectors of the church struggled to integrate their membership - and with success. In the 1960s, in the midst of the Vietnam War, St. Joseph's supported the principle that their church could be a sanctuary to young men who opposed the war as morally reprehensible. About this same time, moved by the requests of homosexual Christians for a place to worship, St. Joseph's opened its doors.
There were costs to each of the liberal stands the church chose to make - costs in terms of time, money, and membership. In 1970, when the then rector Robert Morrison resigned, the vestry of St. Joseph's began considering a merger with St. Matthew's, and invited their rector, Quintin E. Primo, Jr., to serve as priest-in-charge of St. Joseph's.
The merger was completed in 1971, with the St. Matthew's congregation moving over to St. Joseph's church facility. Primo served as rector of the merged congregation from 1971 to 1972, when he became Bishop of Chicago. He was replaced by the Reverend Orris G. Walker, Jr.
Church Leadership
St. Matthew's Episcopal Church
Vicars:
William C. Monroe (1846-1859)
Reverend King (1859-1860)
Samuel Berry (1860-1861)
G. Mott Williams (1881-1887)
W. Warren Wilson (1887-1889)
D. Charles H. Thompson (1890-1893)
Joshua B. Massiah (1893-1906)
Rectors:
George Bundy (1906-1910)
Robert Bagnall (1911-1921)
Everard W. Daniel (1921-1939)
F. Ricksford Meyers (1940-1965)
Robert C. Chapman (1966-1968)
Quintin E. Primo, Jr. (1969-1971)
St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
Rectors:
Paul Faude (1910-1921)
Samuel S. Marquis (1921-1925)
William R. Kinder (1925-1942)
William C. Hamm (1942-1952)
H. Reginald Howden (1953-1956)
Joseph Dickson (1957-1963)
David M. Gracie (1963-1967)
Robert E. Morrison (1967-1970)
St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
Rectors:
Quintin E. Primo, Jr. (1971-1972)
Orris G. Walker, Jr. (1972- )
The records of St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church divide into the following record series: the records of St. Matthew's (before the 1971 merger); the records of St. Joseph's (before the 1971 merger); the records of the merged church (1971 to the present); photographs, oral history project, and Sara Hunter collected materials.
Subjects:
Afro-American churches.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); St. Matthew's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-American churches.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Great Lakes Conference (2nd: 1917: Detroit, Mich.); St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); St. Matthew's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- St. Matthew's Episcopal Church
  The records of St. Matthew's (before 1971) total three linear feet and date primarily from the mid-1920s. Although providing excellent documentation for the years since about 1927, the St. Matthew's series, except for an occasional program or brochure, does not include materials for the first eighty years of the church's existence. Happily, the collection contains published histories and commemorative programs, which help to fill in these missing years.
  The St. Matthew's series has been divided into six subseries: Informational Files, Church Government, Pastors, Church Organizations, Publications, and Scrapbooks.
  - Informational Files
    "Informational Files" consist of manuscript and printed histories written at various dates, commemorative programs, and newspaper clippings about church activities. Also included with this subseries are report documents that the church was required to submit to the state as a non-profit corporation, and to its denominational parent, the Diocese of Michigan.
    - Histories and historical miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Commemorative programs (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Membership list 1941 (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Title abstracts (Box 1)
    - Michigan Non-Profit Corporation Reports 1932-1934 (Box 1)
    - Parochial Reports (to the Diocese of Michigan) 1925-1931 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Church Government
    The subseries, "Church Government," includes files of the proceedings of the church's vestry (1927-1970), Parish Council minutes (1960-1965), and treasurer's records (1924-1970). The researcher will note the absence of church records prior to 1924.
    - Vestry minutes 1927-1970, 1 volumes; 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Parish Council minute book 1960-1965 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's records 1924-1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pastors
    The subseries, "Pastors," consists of correspondence files of F. Ricksford Meyers for the year 1940 only. In addition to church business, the files detail Meyers' concern for his parishioners.
    - F. Ricksford Meyers correspondence 1940, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Robert C. Chapman-testimony re South Africa investments 1969 (Box 1)
  - Church Organizations
    "Church Organizations" consists of records of three of the church's organizations: the Brotherhood of Saint Andrew, the Dorcas Society, and St. Agnes Guild. There is also a scattering of information about other church organizations.
    - Brotherhood of Saint Andrew (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1929-1942, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - Dorcas Society (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - St. Agnes Guild (Box 2)
    - Minutes and miscellanea 1940-1973 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous organizations (Box 2)
  - Publications
    Within "Publications" the researcher will find scattered copies of the church's various newsletters, the earliest dated 1914. Unfortunately, no chronological run of these newsletters seems to have been kept. The same is true of the church's Sunday bulletins. Though some date back to 1945, the bulk of them is for the year 1967.
    - Newsletters: St. Matthew's Record, 1914; untitled news sheet 1928-1929; St. Matthew's Parish News, 1952; The Recorder, 1966; Newsletter, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Bulletins 1945-1969 (mainly 1967), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Programs of church activities (Box 2)
    - "What Every Christian Should Know" (1915), church doctrine and ritual by R.W. Bagnell (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    Some of the earliest dated documents in this series are found in the subseries, "Scrapbooks." Although the contents of the scrapbooks are partially duplicated in other subseries, what makes these scrapbooks especially valuable is the presence of early photographs of church groups and historically informative clippings and programs. The scrapbooks appear to have been created in the 1960s and 1970s, perhaps by the church historian. Unfortunately, the documents were put into the volumes in a random order. Thus, the researcher will have to examine all of the books for information on any given time period.
    - Various dates, 9 volumes (Box 3)
      (these volumes contain a mixture of photographs, clippings, programs, and miscellanea, primarily relating to St. Matthew's; the volumes are not arranged in chronological order)
- St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
  The records of St. Joseph's total four and one-half linear ft. and date from 1884 to 1970 when the two churches merged. Subseries include: Informational Files, Church Government, Publications, Topical Files, Church Organizations, Register of Church Services, and Architectural Blueprints and Drawings. Though there are similarities between the subseries in the two series, there are also important differences. First, the records of St. Joseph's are more fulsome and complete than those of St. Matthew's; second, the St. Joseph's series includes files that reflect the church's involvement with community problems and social issues; and third, the St. Joseph's series includes types of documentation that is not available in the St. Matthew's series, notably information about the church building.
  - Informational Files
    The subseries "Informational Files" is noteworthy, in addition to historical programs and clippings about church activities, for a substantial history of the church written by Alfred H. Povah in 1958.
    - Historical and commemorative programs (Box 4)
    - History of St. Joseph's written by Alfred H. Povah 1958 (Box 4)
    - Historical miscellanea (Box 4)
    - Membership rosters (Box 4)
    - Early document (legal, land contracts, etc.) (Box 4)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Church Government
    "Church Government" is the largest subseries in the St. Joseph's series, and includes a continuous run of vestry minutes dating from 1884 to 1970. Less complete are Parish Council minutes, which cover the years 1931 to 1942 only, and Annual Reports for the period 1959-1969.
    - Vestry minutes 1884-1947, 7 volumes (Box 4)
      (the first vestry meeting was July 22, 1886 the minutes prior to that date are of the church leadership of that time)
    - Vestry minutes 1947-1966, 3 volumes; 10 volumes booklets (Box 5)
    - Vestry minutes 1967-1970, 5 volumes booklets; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Parish Council minutes 1931-1942, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Annual reports 1959-1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Publications
    Within "Publications" the researcher will find a fairly complete run of the St. Joseph Record, 1910-1970. Church bulletins are also found here.
    - St. Joseph's Record, 1910-1970, 1 volumes; 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Bulletins 1927-1968, 27 folders (Box 12)
  - Topical Files
    In "Topical Files" the researcher will find significant documentation of the church's "liberal" position with respect to such issues as the war in Vietnam and its support of those individuals who opposed the war on moral grounds.
    - Black Economic Development Conference 1969 (Box 7)
    - Building Committee minute book 1910 (Box 7)
    - Community Involvement paper circa 1968 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1967-1970 (Box 7)
    - Endowment Fund circa 1940s-circa 1960s (Box 7)
    - Merger 1970 (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea (Box 7)
    - Neighborhood Services proposal 1967 (Box 7)
    - North Woodward Community Council 1963-1965 (Box 7)
    - North Woodward Clergy Association 1967-1969 (Box 7)
    - Revolving Fund 1937-1942 (Box 7)
    - Urban Church Commission 1959-1968 (Box 7)
    - Vietnam War/draft resistors (church position statements) 1969 (Box 7)
  - Church Organizations
    - Church choir minutes 1952-1954 (Box 7)
    - Women's Auxiliary Guild minute book 1942-1953 (Box 7)
  - Architectural blueprints and drawings
    - 1920s (Box 7)
  - Register of Church Services
    - 1942-1963, 1 volumes (Box 7)
- St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
  The third series, St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church, contains the records of the churches merged together. This series dates from 1970 to 1997, and measures approximately four and one-half linear feet.
  Subseries include: Informational Files, Church Government, Topical Files, and Publications. The contents of these subseries are similar to those of St. Joseph's and St. Matthew's previously described. Here again, the researcher will find the run of vestry minutes found in the subseries "Church Government" to be most informative about the activities of the church in the 1970s and 1980s. Also of value is an extensive run of the church's Sunday bulletins since the 1971 merger.
  - Informational Files
    - Historical and background information (Box 7)
    - Anniversary Celebrations (includes programs) (Box 7)
    - St. Matthew's, 130th 1976 (Box 7)
    - St. Matthew's, 135th 1981 (Box 7)
    - St. Joseph's, 100th 1983 (Box 7)
    - St. Matthew's, 140th 1986 (Box 7)
    - St. Matthew's, 150th 1996 (Box 7)
      (includes records of the celebration committee)
    - Biographical information (Box 7)
    - Quintin Primo, Jr (Box 7)
    - Orris Walker, Jr (Box 7)
    - Joseph A. Harmon (Box 7)
  - Church Government
    - Bylaws (Box 8)
    - Vestry minutes 1971-1988, 10 folders; 3 volumes (Box 8)
      (the 3 volumes duplicate to some extent the records found in the yearly folders, but include additional materials as well)
    - Annual reports 1971-1997, 2 folders (Box 9)
      (includes some gaps)
    - Treasurer's reports 1972-1987, 8 folders (Box 9)
      (includes some gaps; treasurer's reports also found in the 3 volumes of vestry minutes, box 7)
  - Topical Files
    - Church personalities (clippings and obituary programs) (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1971-1982, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Dixon, Blair 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Jones, Absalom (about; also related programs) (Box 9)
    - Mayson, the Rt. Rev. H. Irving 1992 (Box 9)
    - Meet The Authors 1992 (Box 9)
      (a program designed to introduce local authors)
    - Merger file 1970-1971 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Remodeling Specifications 1971-1973 (Box 9)
    - Search committee 1996 (Box 9)
    - Vestry Workshop 1983 (Box 9)
    - Woodward Convocation meeting 1972 (Box 9)
  - Publications
    - The Record, circa 1971-1975 (scattered dates) (Box 10)
    - Liturgies, etc. (Box 10)
    - Programs to special services (Box 10)
    - Programs (miscellaneous), 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Album containing bulletins and programs (Box 10)
    - Sunday bulletins 1971-1978 (Box 10)
      (includes gaps for later years)
    - Sunday bulletins 1985-2006 (Box 11)
      (includes gaps)
- SERIES 4: Photographs
  The series, Photographs, consists of approximately .3 linear feet of photographs. In addition to photographs that document the personalities and activities of the two churches, this series also has photographs of the two church buildings, both interiors and exteriors. As noted before, for photographs about St. Matthew's, the researcher should also consult the scrapbooks found in box 3.
  - St. Matthew's Episcopal Church
    - Personalities (Box 13)
    - Groups/activities (Box 13)
    - Building (Box 13)
  - St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
    - Building (Box 13)
  - St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
    - Activities (Box 13)
    - Personalities (church?) (Box 13)
    - Rectors; church personalities (Box 13)
    - Unidentified (Box 13)
    - Photograph album of church personalities and occasions 1993 (Box 13)
- SERIES 5: Oral history project
  Oral History Project (0.2 linear ft.) consists of oral history tapes and transcriptions of interviews with long-time church members.
  - St. Matthew's oral history project (cassette tapes and transcriptions)
    - Cassey, Geneva Jefferson (Box 13)
    - Christman, Robert (Box 13)
    - Miller, Catherine (Box 13)
  - St. Joseph's oral history project
    - Dickinson, Joseph (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Release form, questions to ask (Box 13)
- Series 6: Sara Hunter collected papers
  The Sara Hunter collected papers includes programs, obsequies for members, clippings, and miscellaneous other materials accumulated by this long-time member. The series dates from the 1980s to the present, but also including some earlier copied papers.
  - Programs, obsequies for members, clippings, and miscellanea relating to church history 1980s-2006 (Box 14)
    (unprocessed)